(All people, organizations, locations, and incidents...)
(모든 사람, 조직, 장소, 사건...)
(in this drama are fictitious.)
(이 드라마의 내용은 허구입니다.)
- Yes. - We're all getting out!
- 네. - 우리 모두 나가요!
We should capture one of them and hear them out.
그 중 하나를 포착해서 들어봐야 합니다.
Got it.
알았어요.
They wouldn't have gotten far, so spread out and search.
멀리 가지 못했을 테니 널리 퍼져서 수색해 보세요.
Wouldn't they have made a run for it?
그들은 그것을 위해 도망치지 않았을까요?
I don't know what they have in mind,
그 사람들이 무슨 생각을 하고 있는지는 모르겠지만,
but they won't leave her behind.
하지만 그들은 그녀를 뒤에 남겨두지 않을 것입니다.
They don't seem like your average school buddies,
평범한 학교 친구들 같지는 않은데,
but I don't know what their story is.
하지만 그들의 이야기가 무엇인지는 모르겠습니다.
- Tell me about it. - Right.
- 그것에 대해 말해 보세요. - 오른쪽.
Let's get on our separate ways.
각자의 길을 갑시다.
The doors were unlocked, and there isn't a problem.
문은 열려 있었고 문제는 없었습니다.
Look here, mister. Unbelievable.
여기 보세요, 아저씨. 믿을 수 없는.
How stupid can you be?
얼마나 어리석을 수 있습니까?
We should find out what's going on outside.
밖에서 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지 알아내야 해요.
- I'm not interested. - Is that so?
- 관심 없어요. - 그렇습니까?
Then, you should be on your way.
그렇다면 당신은 가던 길을 가야 합니다.
You'll be heartbroken...
마음이 아프실 거에요...
if your mother isn't at the nursing home.
어머니가 요양원에 계시지 않으면요.
I mean...
내 말은 ...
- Hold on. - Hey.
- 잠깐만요. - 여기요.
What are you talking about?
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요?
I asked my boys outside to look out for your mother.
밖에 있는 내 아들들에게 네 엄마를 찾아달라고 부탁했어.
Don't you dare lay a finger on her,
감히 그녀에게 손가락질도 하지 마세요.
you sick psycho.
이 병든 정신병자야.
It's why we should help each other out.
그렇기 때문에 우리는 서로 도와야 합니다.
Come on, darn it. Stop being so scary.
어서, 젠장. 너무 무서워하지 마세요.
What are you glaring at me for?
당신은 무엇 때문에 나를 노려보는 거죠?
After I get you the kids,
내가 너에게 아이들을 데려온 후,
we won't see each other again.
우리는 다시는 볼 수 없습니다.
Sure thing.
확실한 것.
I don't care about the boys, so kill them all.
나는 그 소년들에게 관심이 없으므로 모두 죽여라.
- Only bring the girls. - Sure.
- 여자들만 데려오세요. - 확신하는.
What was her name again? Right, it was Bo Ra.
그 사람 이름은 또 뭐였지? 그렇죠, 보라였습니다.
Make sure she isn't harmed in any way.
그녀가 어떤 식으로든 피해를 입지 않도록 하세요.
She's one I must groom.
그녀는 내가 손질해야 할 사람입니다.
It's been a while, and I'm getting excited.
시간이 좀 지났고 점점 신이 나네요.
Darn.
꿰매다.
The one with the glasses is more my type though.
그래도 안경을 쓴 사람이 내 타입에 더 가깝습니다.
I see you like those in glasses. Go ahead, then.
당신이 안경을 좋아하는 것 같군요. 그럼 계속하세요.
You can take that one if you want.
원하시면 그걸 가져가셔도 됩니다.
- She's too docile, which is boring. - Okay.
- 너무 얌전해서 지루해요. - 좋아요.
Get up, will you?
일어나요, 그렇죠?
Hey.
여기요.
Hey, keep walking.
이봐, 계속 걸어.
I must've lost weight while not being able to eat and all.
밥도 못 먹고 살이 빠졌나 봐요.
My pants keep slipping down.
바지가 계속 흘러내려요.
Let's hurry up and eat.
얼른 먹고 먹자.
I'll enjoy my meal and also the one with glasses.
식사는 물론, 안경을 쓴 식사도 즐겨보겠습니다.
Gosh, it's nice to be out,
맙소사, 밖에 나가서 반가워요
but the fine dust...
그런데 미세먼지..
Are you really going off on your own?
정말 혼자 떠나는 건가요?
- What a moron. - What? Unbelievable.
- 정말 바보 같군요. - 무엇? 믿을 수 없는.
Hey, hairy guy.
안녕, 털이 많은 남자.
Wait for me, hairy guy. Are we going this way?
기다려라, 털이 많은 녀석. 우리 이쪽으로 가는 거야?
Shoot.
사격.
Keep yourself hidden down to your strands of hair
머리카락 사이로 자신을 숨기세요
Kids, where are you?
얘들아, 어디 있어?
Let's play.
놀자.
Here you are!
여기 있어요!
I guess not.
나는 아닌 것 같아요.
Kill...
죽여라...
the boys.
소년들.
While the girls...
반면 소녀들은...
There they are.
거기 있습니다.
Darn it.
젠장.
Stop.
멈추다.
(Infirmary)
(의료실)
Hey, shouldn't we finish up what we started earlier?
야, 아까 시작한 일을 끝내면 안 될까?
Why don't we swap clothes?
우리 옷을 바꾸는 게 어때?
Would it kill you to give me a livelier response?
나에게 더 생생한 답변을 주면 당신을 죽일 수 있습니까?
Kids!
어린이!
Where are you going?
어디 가세요?
This has been my home for years, you know.
아시다시피 이곳은 수년간 내 집이었습니다.
I know this place like the back of my hand.
나는 이곳을 내 손등처럼 알고 있다.
Darn, you're not here.
젠장, 당신은 여기 없어요.
Why aren't you here?
왜 여기 없나요?
You little turds.
이 작은 똥.
Keep yourself hidden
자신을 숨겨라
Down to your strands of hair
머리카락 한 가닥까지
What...
뭐...
Are you kidding me, you little freaks?
장난하는 거야, 이 괴물들아?
Where the heck are you? Get out here!
도대체 어디 있는 거야? 여기서 나가세요!
What the heck?
도대체 뭐야?
You little cow.
이 작은 소.
Darn it.
젠장.
You ugly little cow.
이 못생긴 소.
Get back here, you cow! Darn it!
여기로 돌아가라, 이 소야! 젠장!
What the...
뭐야...
Hey! Get back here!
이봐! 여기로 돌아가세요!
You little cow.
이 작은 소.
Are you kidding me?
농담하는 거야?
Don't waste my energy and get out here, darn it.
내 에너지를 낭비하지 말고 여기로 나가세요.
Open up.
열어라.
You little cow!
이 작은 소!
Are you kidding me?
농담하는 거야?
Get out here!
여기서 나가세요!
Darn cow.
젠장 소.
Who's there?
거기 누구 있어요?
What the heck is that?
그게 대체 뭐야?
Darn it!
젠장!
Darn...
젠장...
What the...
뭐야...
No...
아니...
I see he screams when he has orgasms.
나는 그가 오르가즘을 느낄 때 비명을 지르는 것을 봅니다.
You darn morons.
이 멍청한 놈들아.
How hard is it to catch a couple of kids?
두 명의 아이들을 잡는 것이 얼마나 어렵습니까?
Are you kidding me?
농담하는 거야?
Darn it!
젠장!
It has begun.
그것은 시작되었습니다.
Oh, no.
안 돼.
Will the others be all right?
다른 사람들은 괜찮을까요?
Hang in there, Ae Seol.
조금만 참아라 설애씨.
Wait, is that a sphere?
잠깐만요, 저거 구형인가요?
- Where did it come from? - There are four of them.
- 어디서 나온 거야? - 4개가 있어요.
- And they're drawing near. - Oh, no.
- 그리고 그들이 가까이 다가오고 있어요. - 안 돼.
At this speed, they'll reach the building in minutes.
이 속도라면 몇 분 안에 건물에 도착할 거예요.
We have no choice. We should let them go.
우리에게는 선택의 여지가 없습니다. 우리는 그들을 놓아주어야 합니다.
Wait.
기다리다.
This might be our way to save Ae Seol.
이것이 애설을 살리는 길일지도 모른다.
Lure the spheres your way while we get to Ae Seol.
애설에 도착하는 동안 구체를 유인해 보세요.
And be careful.
그리고 조심하세요.
Will it be okay? We'll all be in danger.
괜찮을까요? 우리 모두 위험에 처하게 될 거예요.
There's no other way at this point.
지금으로서는 다른 방법이 없습니다.
It'll work out.
잘 될 거예요.
Ae Seol is stronger than you think.
애설씨는 생각보다 강해요.
- Okay, let's open this door. - Hurry.
- 알았어, 이 문을 열어보자. - 서두르다.
- You must have the keys. - Unlock it.
- 열쇠가 있어야 합니다. - 잠금을 해제하세요.
- Hurry, will you? - There we go.
- 서둘러요? - 됐어요.
And then...
그리고...
The door will now open.
이제 문이 열릴 것입니다.
- Did it work? - We need the rest inside.
- 효과가 있었나요? - 나머지는 안에 필요해요.
- You pricks!
- 이 멍청아!
Here they come.
여기 그들이 온다.
Who knew I'd be playing Tag with them?
내가 그들과 함께 태그 게임을 할 줄 누가 알았겠어요?
Just don't let them catch up.
그들이 따라잡지 못하게 하세요.
Are you telling me you're not getting horny?
화나지 않는다고 말하는 거야?
There's no need to be on full Rambo mode.
전체 람보 모드에 있을 필요는 없습니다.
No one's here.
여기에는 아무도 없습니다.
The one with the glasses seems to like the colour white...
안경 쓴 사람은 흰색을 좋아하는 것 같은데...
like the Gray in my hair.
내 머리의 회색처럼.
What?
무엇?
I'm also armed, you freak.
나도 무장했어, 이 괴물아.
What? I'll shoot, darn it.
무엇? 내가 쏠게, 젠장.
Anyway, the one with the glasses likes the colour white...
그나저나 안경 쓴 사람은 흰색을 좋아하는구나...
like the Gray in my hair.
내 머리의 회색처럼.
Where are you going?
어디 가세요?
What the...
뭐야...
If you keep moving about on your own,
계속 혼자 움직이다보면
I won't let you have fun.
나는 당신이 재미있게 지내도록 두지 않을 것입니다.
What on earth?
도대체 뭐야?
Did the kids do this?
아이들이 이런 짓을 했나?
I think someone else is in play.
다른 사람이 게임 중인 것 같아요.
Something isn't right.
뭔가 잘못되었습니다.
I can't take it anymore. I'm leaving.
더 이상 참을 수 없습니다. 나는 떠난다.
What the heck is this? Darn it.
이게 대체 뭐야? 젠장.
My gosh.
맙소사.
Get off me!
나한테서 떨어져!
Darn it!
젠장!
Save me! Do something!
나를 구해주세요! 뭔가를 해보세요!
Oh, my gosh.
아, 이런.
Save me!
나를 구해주세요!
Jerk.
바보.
For goodness' sake. Bo Ra.
세상에. 보라.
You couldn't hold it in and moved on your own?
참지 못하고 스스로 움직였나요?
Stupid No Ae Seol is alone.
바보 노애설은 혼자다.
Jerks.
바보.
Let's go.
갑시다.
- We have to get out immediately. - Why? What's going on?
- 당장 나가야 해요. - 왜? 무슨 일이야?
Everyone's attacked.
모두가 공격을 받았습니다.
Those little brats?
그 작은 놈들?
It's not the kids.
아이들이 아닙니다.
Then who?
그럼 누구요?
I don't know.
모르겠습니다.
I think it's a weird monster.
이상한 괴물인 것 같아요.
A monster?
괴물?
What are you talking about?
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요?
You jerk. Did you kill them?
멍청아. 당신이 그들을 죽였나요?
I saw it with my own eyes.
나는 내 눈으로 그것을 보았다.
We need to get out quick. If you want to live.
빨리 나가야 해요. 살고 싶다면.
What are you talking about? Darn it!
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요? 젠장!
What's that?
그게 뭐야?
Gosh. Hey.
이런. 여기요.
Hey. Be careful. Hey.
여기요. 조심하세요. 여기요.
Hey! Shoot!
여기요! 사격!
Why isn't it dying? Hey! Look at this.
왜 죽지 않는 걸까요? 여기요! 이것 좀 보세요.
- Hey. Oh, gosh. - Gosh!
- 여기요. 아, 이런. - 이런!
For goodness' sake.
세상에.
Shoot. What is it?
사격. 그것은 무엇입니까?
Darn it!
젠장!
He got what he deserved.
그는 마땅한 것을 얻었습니다.
Let's hurry and find Ae Seol and get out of here.
서둘러 애설을 찾아 여기서 나가자.
For goodness' sake.
세상에.
She's not there?
그녀는 거기에 없나요?
For goodness' sake. Where is she?
세상에. 그녀는 어디에 있나요?
Perhaps...
아마도...
No Ae Seol!
아니 설애씨!
- For goodness' sake. - No Ae Seol!
- 맙소사. - 아니 애설!
No Ae Seol!
아니 설애씨!
- Yes?
- 예?
- Bo Ra. - Are you okay?
- 보라. - 괜찮으세요?
- No Ae Seol! - Ae Seol!
- 아니 애설! - 애설!
You're okay, right?
괜찮아요?
Yes, I'm okay.
네, 괜찮아요.
What about others?
다른 사람들은 어떻습니까?
They're fine. Let's go first.
그들은 괜찮습니다. 먼저 가자.
Let's go.
갑시다.
Oh, my gosh!
오, 맙소사!
Go ahead!
계속하세요!
Cho Young Sin!
조영신!
They're here again!
그들이 또 여기 왔어요!
I told you we shouldn't have come! Darn it!
우리가 오지 말았어야 했다고 말했잖아! 젠장!
- Run! - For goodness' sake.
- 달리다! - 맙소사.
Darn it.
젠장.
Gosh. Shoot!
이런. 사격!
- Hee Rak! - Oh, gosh! Shoot!
- 희락! - 아, 이런! 사격!
Don't come!
오지 마세요!
Stay down!
가만히 있어!
Darn it. I'm done for.
젠장. 난 이제 끝났어.
For goodness' sake!
세상에!
Come here, you wench!
이리 오세요, 이 아가씨!
Why? What?
왜? 무엇?
Come here.
이리 오세요.
You witch!
마녀야!
You ruined everything!
당신은 모든 것을 망쳤습니다!
Darn it!
젠장!
You seemed unlucky since the first time I saw you. Come here.
당신은 처음 봤을 때부터 운이 좋지 않은 것 같았어요. 이리 오세요.
I'll make a hole in your head. You witch. Come here.
네 머리에 구멍을 뚫어줄게 마녀야. 이리 오세요.
Watch carefully.
주의 깊게 관찰하세요.
Look.
바라보다.
You're crazy.
당신은 미쳤어요.
You witch. Are you pretending to be kind?
마녀야. 친절한 척 하는 거야?
For goodness' sake.
세상에.
Oh, gosh! You witch! Seriously!
아, 이런! 마녀야! 진지하게!
Gosh. Shoot!
이런. 사격!
Gosh. Darn it!
이런. 젠장!
You witch. Seriously!
마녀야. 진지하게!
Shoot. You brat. I'll kill you.
사격. 이 녀석. 나는 당신을 죽일 것이다.
Yes. Shoot them all.
예. 모두 쏴라.
Kill all the witches here.
여기서 마녀를 모두 죽여라.
Oh, shoot. Seriously.
아, 쏴. 진지하게.
What are you doing standing there doing nothing? You fool!
아무것도 안 하고 거기 서서 뭐 하는 거야? 바보야!
Shoot them! Shoot to let them meet their moms. You fool.
쏴버려! 그들이 엄마를 만날 수 있도록 촬영하세요. 바보야.
Shoot them! Darn it!
쏴버려! 젠장!
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
For goodness' sake.
세상에.
I was curious...
궁금했어요...
why those appeared out of nowhere.
왜 갑자기 나타난 걸까요?
I think I know why now.
이제 그 이유를 알 것 같아요.
It's because humans...
인간이니까...
are trash.
쓰레기야.
They're here to clean up.
그들은 청소를 하러 왔습니다.
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
Bo Ra. You're bleeding.
보라. 피가 나고 있어요.
- Jerks. - Are you okay?
- 바보. - 괜찮으세요?
I'm fine.
잘 지내요.
(Original Work: "Duty After School" from Naver Webtoon)
(원작 : 네이버웹툰 '방과후의 의무')
(Duty After School)
(방과 후 의무)
(Yongwon Metropolitan Hospital)
(용원도립병원)
What shall we do with Soo Chul?
수철이는 어떻게 할까요?
Shall we bury him?
그를 묻어볼까요?
We have to take him.
그를 데려가야 해요.
How can we leave him here?
어떻게 그를 여기에 남겨 둘 수 있습니까?
Soo Chul.
수철.
No.
아니요.
How did he fall?
그는 어떻게 넘어졌습니까?
What was with the gunfire?
총격은 어떻게 됐나요?
There was no sphere nearby.
근처에는 구체가 없었습니다.
Shoot.
사격.
First,
첫째,
let's go back with Soo Chul before it gets too dark.
더 어두워지기 전에 수철이랑 같이 돌아가자.
What?
무엇?
Take a look at this.
이것 좀 보세요.
What is that?
저게 뭐에요?
- That's... - It's a ballot.
- 그게... - 투표용지예요.
Why is that here?
그게 왜 여기에 있나요?
This is mine.
이건 내꺼야
Hey, what are you talking about?
무슨 소리 하는 거야?
It's my ballot from yesterday.
어제 제 투표용지입니다.
It's mine for sure.
그것은 확실히 내 것입니다.
But why is that here?
그런데 그게 왜 여기에 있는 걸까요?
(Yongdu Service Area)
(용두 휴게소)
We'll be leaving now.
이제 출발하겠습니다.
You guys should change your minds too.
여러분도 생각을 바꿔야 합니다.
There's no reason to stay here when the CSAT has been cancelled.
수능이 취소됐는데 여기 계속 있을 이유가 없잖아요.
All right.
괜찮은.
I'll talk to the others when they get here.
다른 사람들이 여기 오면 얘기해 볼게요.
All right, then. Be careful.
그럼요. 조심하세요.
Stay alive.
살아있어라.
- Bye. - Best of luck.
- 안녕. - 행운을 빕니다.
- Be careful.
- 조심하세요.
Wait.
기다리다.
Well...
음...
about the walkie-talkie.
워키토키에 대해서.
What you guys said about someone breaking it on purpose...
누군가 고의로 깨뜨렸다고 하던데요...
Is there not even a single chance that you could have been mistaken?
당신이 실수했을 가능성은 단 한 번도 없나요?
- The thing is... - You're right.
- 문제는... - 당신 말이 맞아요.
We could have been mistaken.
우리는 실수했을 수도 있습니다.
- We'll get going, then. - Bye.
- 그럼 출발하겠습니다. - 안녕.
- Seriously.
- 진지하게.
We should tell them. Are we really going to just leave like this...
우리는 그들에게 말해야 합니다. 우리 정말 이대로 떠날 것인가...
without telling them?
그들에게 말하지 않고?
If it makes them feel comfortable...
그 사람들이 편해지면..
to think that we were mistaken, then we made the right choice.
우리가 틀렸다고 생각하면 올바른 선택을 한 것입니다.
What are you talking about?
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요?
It'll only get harder once we start losing each other's trust.
서로의 신뢰를 잃기 시작하면 상황은 더욱 어려워질 것입니다.
- Keep moving. - But...
- 계속 움직여요. - 하지만...
It doesn't make sense.
그것은 말이 되지 않습니다.
Why would Do Soo Chul rig the ballots?
수철은 왜 투표용지를 조작했을까?
But what is this, then?
그런데 이건 뭐죠?
It's proof that our votes have been manipulated thus far.
지금까지 우리의 투표가 조작되었다는 증거입니다.
Don't jump to conclusions.
성급하게 결론을 내리지 마십시오.
Even after seeing this?
이걸 보고도?
Hey, that's just nonsense.
이봐, 그건 말도 안되는 소리야.
What is this situation?
이 상황은 무엇입니까?
Only Soo Chul will know.
수철만이 알 것이다.
That means we've been needlessly suffering because of Do Soo Chul.
도수철 때문에 쓸데없는 고생을 했다는 뜻이다.
Hey, you lunatic, watch your mouth! He's dead!
야, 미친놈아, 입 조심해! 그는 죽었어!
Darn it! Then what else am I supposed to do?
젠장! 그럼 난 또 뭘 해야 하지?
- Darn you. - Stop!
- 젠장. - 멈추다!
I can't think because of you guys.
너희들 때문에 생각을 할 수가 없어
Hasn't Soo Chul been acting strange recently?
최근 수철이 이상한 행동을 하지 않았나요?
He's been awfully quiet.
그는 정말 조용했어요.
Do you think...
당신은 생각합니까 ...
he committed suicide because he couldn't handle the pain?
고통을 이기지 못해 자살했다고요?
Someone also committed suicide at the garrison due to depression.
우울증으로 수비대에서 자살한 사람도 있다.
No, it's not suicide.
아니요, 자살이 아닙니다.
I told her she could get back to me slowly.
나는 그녀에게 천천히 다시 연락해도 된다고 말했다.
But even if I get rejected, I won't give up.
하지만 거절당하더라도 포기하지 않을 거예요.
I'm going to keep trying until my feelings get accepted.
내 감정이 받아들여질 때까지 계속 노력할 거예요.
There's no way he would've committed suicide.
그가 자살했을 리가 없습니다.
Then why did he die?
그렇다면 그는 왜 죽었는가?
You want to come clean now?
지금 깨끗이 하고 싶나요?
Do you think the others will be understanding?
다른 사람들도 이해해 줄 것 같나요?
Gosh.
이런.
Is anyone there?
거기 누구 있어요?
What?
무엇?
Earlier...
이전에...
No way.
절대 안돼.
There's no way.
방법이 없습니다.
That can't be true. Think about it.
그것은 사실일 수 없습니다. 생각해 보세요.
They broke it on purpose? How does that make sense?
일부러 깨뜨린 걸까요? 그게 어떻게 이해가 되나요?
What if it's true?
그것이 사실이라면 어떨까요?
If it's true, who in the world broke it?
그것이 사실이라면, 도대체 누가 깨뜨렸는가?
Gosh, this is driving me crazy.
이런, 이게 날 미치게 만드네요.
- They must be here. - Hey.
- 여기 있을 거에요. - 여기요.
Let's keep it to ourselves for now.
지금은 우리끼리만 간직하자.
- Why? - Hey, it could end up...
- 왜? - 이봐, 끝날 수도 있어...
creating tension between everyone.
모두 사이에 긴장감을 조성합니다.
Let's tell Yu Jung at a later time.
나중에 유정에게 말하자.
She's right.
그녀 말이 맞아요.
We don't even know what actually happened with the walkie-talkie.
우리는 무전기에 실제로 무슨 일이 일어났는지조차 모릅니다.
Fine.
괜찮은.
- I don't know. - Seriously.
- 모르겠습니다. - 진지하게.
Bo Ra got hurt pretty bad.
보라가 많이 다쳤어요.
I feel like I'm going to die.
나는 죽을 것 같은 느낌이 든다.
Darn it, we have to deal with criminals on top of spheres.
젠장, 우리는 구체 위에서 범죄자들을 처리해야 합니다.
Hey, it just happens like that.
아, 그냥 그런 일이 일어나네요.
- Stop being so annoying. - Come on.
- 너무 짜증나게 하지 마세요. - 어서 해봐요.
Oh, my gosh! Yeon Bo Ra, are you okay?
오, 맙소사! 연보라 씨, 괜찮아요?
- What? - Be quiet. Stop making a fuss.
- 무엇? - 조용히 하세요. 소란을 피우지 마세요.
Yeon Ju isn't here. What should we do?
연주는 여기 없어요. 우리는 무엇을 해야 합니까?
Oh, right. Emergency first aid.
아, 그렇죠. 응급처치.
Bo Ra, let's go.
보라야, 가자.
I'll take care of it on my own.
내가 직접 처리하겠습니다.
Bo Ra, just go and get treated.
보라야 그냥 가서 치료받아라
Let go. I can walk on my own.
가자. 나는 스스로 걸을 수 있다.
- Hey. - Don't bother me.
- 여기요. - 귀찮게 하지 마세요.
Did something happen?
무슨 일이 있었나요?
How did Bo Ra get hurt?
보라는 어떻게 다쳤나요?
Were there a lot of spheres?
구체가 많았나요?
It wasn't the spheres.
그것은 구체가 아니었습니다.
What? Then what was it?
무엇? 그렇다면 그것은 무엇이었나요?
But why weren't you guys keeping watch?
그런데 너희들은 왜 감시하지 않았느냐?
- What? - Well...
- 무엇? - 잘...
The thing is...
문제는 ...
something came up.
뭔가 떠올랐다.
Right. Did you guys find a walkie-talkie?
오른쪽. 여러분, 무전기를 찾으셨나요?
- Darn it.
- 젠장.
No, there weren't any.
아니요, 전혀 없었습니다.
You said there would be!
있을 거라고 했잖아!
You were so confident!
정말 자신감이 넘치셨어요!
Why are you raising your voice?
왜 목소리를 높이는 걸까요?
Hey, is that our fault?
야, 그게 우리 잘못이야?
- We almost died. - Darn it.
- 우리는 거의 죽을 뻔했어요. - 젠장.
Why?
왜?
What happened?
무슨 일이에요?
Forget it. I'm too exhausted...
잊어버리세요. 너무 지쳤어...
to talk right now.
지금 당장 얘기하자.
Hey.
여기요.
We said we'd keep it to ourselves.
우리는 그것을 우리끼리만 간직하겠다고 말했습니다.
All right.
괜찮은.
I'll rub the ointment now.
이제 연고를 바르겠습니다.
Thanks.
감사해요.
And sorry for acting on my own.
그리고 내 마음대로 행동해서 미안해요.
My body just reacted instinctively.
내 몸은 본능적으로 반응했다.
Stop trying to build a relationship with me.
나와 관계를 구축하려는 노력을 중단하십시오.
I couldn't help it.
나는 그것을 도울 수 없었다.
After my parents got divorced,
부모님이 이혼하신 후,
no one wanted to raise me, so I was left with my grandma.
아무도 나를 키우고 싶어하지 않았기 때문에 나는 할머니와 함께 남겨졌습니다.
I never said I was curious.
저는 한번도 궁금하다고 말한 적이 없습니다.
I'm just making an excuse...
핑계만 대고 있는데...
because I'm so sorry.
정말 미안하거든요.
- Hey. - Yes?
- 여기요. - 예?
Didn't I hurt my ear?
나 귀 다친거 아니었어?
Sorry. I'll wrap it again.
죄송합니다. 다시 포장하겠습니다.
It's okay. I'll ask Yeon Ju to help me later.
괜찮아요. 나중에 연주한테 도와달라고 할게요.
By the way...
그런데...
Never mind.
신경쓰지 마세요.
What's that look on your face?
당신의 얼굴에 그 표정은 무엇입니까?
- Are you okay? - Do you think so? I got shot.
- 괜찮으세요? - 그렇게 생각하세요? 나는 총에 맞았습니다.
Yeon Bo Ra, at the penitentiary, No Ae Seol...
연보라, 교도소에서 노애설…
You don't have to explain.
설명할 필요는 없습니다.
Bo Ra.
보라.
I was shocked earlier.
나는 일찍 충격을 받았습니다.
I didn't die. Are you my boyfriend or what?
나는 죽지 않았다. 당신은 내 남자 친구입니까, 아니면 뭐예요?
Why were you shocked?
왜 충격을 받았나요?
Why? Do you want me to be your boyfriend?
왜? 내가 당신의 남자친구가 되길 바라나요?
What are you saying?
무슨 말을 하는 거야?
- Hey. - The others are back. Let's go.
- 여기요. - 다른 사람들이 돌아왔어. 갑시다.
- You guys went through a lot. - Yes.
- 수고가 많으셨어요. - 예.
- Guys, you're here. - You're here.
- 얘들아, 왔구나. - 여기 있어요.
- Soon Yi! - Good work.
-순이! - 잘했어요.
- Soon Yi, Yeon Ju. - What's wrong?
- 이순이, 연주. - 무슨 일이야?
- What's wrong, Yeon Ju? - Soon Yi, Yeon Ju.
- 무슨 일이야, 연주야? - 이순이, 연주.
- What is it? - What's going on?
- 그게 뭐죠? - 무슨 일이에요?
- What?
- 무엇?
What is this?
이게 뭔가요?
Where's Soo Chul?
수철은 어디 있어요?
Come on. Answer us.
어서 해봐요. 우리에게 대답해주세요.
Why aren't you saying anything? You're making me anxious!
왜 아무 말도 안 해요? 당신은 나를 불안하게 만들고 있어요!
Hey, Kwon Il Ha.
안녕하세요, 권일하님.
Why aren't you talking?
왜 말을 안 해요?
Chi Yeol.
치열.
No.
아니요.
What happened?
무슨 일이 일어났나요?
Say something!
뭐라고 말해보세요!
(Convenience store)
(편의점)
Soo Chul...
수철...
Soo Chul.
수철.
Poor Soo Chul.
불쌍한 수철.
Soo Chul...
수철...
What's this?
이건 뭐죠?
The ballot Soo Chul had.
수철이 가지고 있던 투표용지.
There were three dissenting votes.
반대표는 3개였습니다.
Tell me why Soo Chul...
수철이 왜 그랬는지 말해주세요...
had these.
이것들이 있었어요.
What the...
뭐야...
What are these?
이것들은 무엇입니까?
Why are the dissenting votes here?
반대표가 왜 여기에 있나요?
I voted against staying yesterday.
나는 어제 머무르는 것에 반대했다.
The fact he hid these...
그 사람이 이걸 숨겼다는 사실이...
was to fool us into thinking that more voted to stay.
더 많은 사람들이 잔류에 투표했다고 생각하도록 우리를 속이는 것이 었습니다.
Who fooled us?
누가 우리를 속였나요?
Are you saying that Soo Chul did?
수철이 그랬다는 겁니까?
What are you talking about?
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요?
I asked Soo Chul to destroy the ballots.
나는 수철에게 투표용지를 파기하라고 부탁했다.
That must be why he had them.
그것이 그가 그것을 가지고 있었던 이유임에 틀림없다.
Why did he only have ballots that were against the idea?
왜 그는 그 생각에 반대하는 투표용지만 가지고 있었나요?
And three of them?
그리고 그 중 세 명은요?
It's proof that the poll was rigged.
여론조사가 조작됐다는 증거다.
Don't jump to conclusions.
성급하게 결론을 내리지 마십시오.
Soo Chul had no reason to do that.
수철은 그럴 이유가 없었다.
What are you all barking about?
다들 무슨 소리를 하고 있는 거야?
Tell me so that I can understand.
내가 이해할 수 있도록 말해주세요.
Guys, hold on.
여러분, 잠깐만요.
Why are we suspecting one another?
왜 우리는 서로를 의심하는 걸까요?
This will only lead to misunderstandings.
이는 오해만 불러일으킬 뿐입니다.
Then let's get to the truth right now.
그렇다면 지금 당장 진실을 알아봅시다.
If the poll wasn't rigged,
여론조사가 조작되지 않았다면
today's poll will produce the same result.
오늘 여론조사도 같은 결과를 낳을 것이다.
Raise your hand if you voted X.
X에 투표하셨다면 손을 들어주세요.
Hey.
안녕.
We shouldn't be raising hands...
우리는 손을 들면 안 되는데...
Why are you stopping us?
왜 우리를 막는 겁니까?
Wang Tae Man,
왕태만,
you're acting awfully suspicious.
당신은 정말 의심스러운 행동을 하고 있습니다.
What?
무엇?
You've been losing your cool today,
너 오늘 냉정을 잃었어.
- and I'd rather you shut your trap. - Shut my trap?
- 그리고 차라리 덫을 닫았으면 좋겠어요. - 내 함정을 닫아?
- That's right. - Hey!
- 좋아요. - 여기요!
- What? - I can swear too, you know.
- 무엇? - 나도 맹세할 수 있어요.
Go ahead, then.
그럼 계속하세요.
Guys, stop.
얘들아, 그만해
What the...
뭐야...
Unbelievable.
믿을 수 없다.
Darn it.
젠장.
Let's calm down and talk this out.
진정하고 이것에 대해 이야기합시다.
Soo Chul...
수철...
How did he die?
그는 어떻게 죽었나요?
Squad Two, don't you know anything?
2부대, 아무것도 모르시나요?
Say something.
말해보세요.
Soo Chul...
수철...
I heard him argue before dying.
나는 그가 죽기 전에 논쟁하는 것을 들었습니다.
- What?
- 무엇?
Soo Chul...
수철...
- What if it weren't an accident? - Kim Chi Yeol.
- 사고가 아니었다면? -김치열.
What on earth are you saying?
도대체 무슨 말을 하는 거야?
Who did Soo Chul argue with?
수철은 누구와 말다툼을 했나?
Are you sure about it?
확실합니까?
Why are you only mentioning it now?
왜 이제서야 언급하는 겁니까?
I was too startled earlier to put two and two together.
나는 너무 일찍 두 개와 두 개를 합치기에는 너무 놀랐습니다.
It's why I didn't say anything.
그래서 나는 아무 말도 하지 않았다.
What on earth is going on?
도대체 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는 걸까요?
First,
첫 번째,
we must know who Soo Chul argued with in the hospital.
수철이 병원에서 누구와 말다툼을 했는지 알아야 한다.
Tell me...
말해봐...
where you were...
당신은 어디에 있었나요?
and what you were doing at the time.
그리고 그 당시 당신은 무엇을 하고 있었는지.
What?
무엇?
Are you suspecting us?
우리를 의심하고 있나요?
Are you out of your mind? You're asking for our whereabouts?
정신이 나갔나요? 우리의 행방을 묻는 겁니까?
Tell us where you were first!
처음에 어디 있었는지 알려주세요!
Why should we believe you, anyway?
그런데 왜 우리가 당신을 믿어야 합니까?
I'm not saying we should suspect each other.
나는 우리가 서로를 의심해야 한다고 말하는 것이 아닙니다.
We should at least find out how Soo Chul died.
최소한 수철이 어떻게 죽었는지 알아내야 한다.
Then...
그럼...
What you're saying is that...
당신이 말하는 것은...
one of them...
그 중 하나 ...
killed Soo Chul.
수철을 죽였다.
- What? - Ha Na, watch your mouth...
- 무엇? - 하나야, 입 조심해...
and don't say whatever comes to mind.
그리고 생각나는 대로 말하지 마세요.
What if Soo Chul didn't trip and fall?
만약 수철이가 넘어지지 않았다면?
It means someone killed him.
누군가 그를 죽였다는 뜻이다.
As if that makes sense!
마치 말이 되는 것처럼요!
Stop it. My head's about to explode.
그만해요. 머리가 터질 것 같아요.
Let's first confirm what we can.
먼저 우리가 할 수 있는 것을 확인해 봅시다.
We have proof that the poll was rigged,
여론조사가 조작되었다는 증거가 있습니다.
so let's figure that out first.
그럼 먼저 그것을 알아봅시다.
Kim Yu Jung, tell us. You probably know what's going on.
김유정씨, 말해 보세요. 당신은 아마 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지 알고 있을 것입니다.
Why won't you tell us? Speak up!
왜 우리에게 말하지 않는 거죠? 말해보세요!
Don't badger her like that.
그녀를 그렇게 오소리하지 마십시오.
Jang Soo, maybe you were in on it as well.
장수 씨, 아마 당신도 거기에 있었을 거예요.
- This isn't time to take sides. - Hey, don't.
- 지금은 한쪽 편을 들 때가 아닙니다. - 하지 마세요.
Tae Man, why are you advocating for them?
태만씨, 왜 그들을 옹호하는 겁니까?
- Maybe you're in on it too. - I'm in on it too?
- 아마 당신도 그 일에 동참하고 있을 거예요. - 나도 그 일에 참여하고 있나요?
Hey, don't push your luck.
이봐, 행운을 믿지 마세요.
Having a mouth doesn't mean you can say anything.
입이 있다고 해서 아무 말도 할 수 있는 것은 아닙니다.
- Darn you. - Guys, let's calm down.
- 젠장. - 얘들아, 진정하자.
She's right. We're too worked up.
그녀 말이 맞아요. 우리는 너무 힘들어요.
How can one not be?
어떻게 그렇지 않을 수 있습니까?
We almost died today.
오늘 우리는 거의 죽을 뻔했습니다.
If that isn't the case, explain yourself.
그렇지 않다면 스스로 설명하십시오.
Answer the darn question!
그 질문에 답해보세요!
- You! - That's enough!
- 너! - 충분해요!
Let go of me, you jerk.
날 놔, 이 멍청아.
This has been a touchy issue for you today.
이것은 오늘 당신에게 민감한 문제였습니다.
You were in on it for sure!
당신은 확실히 그것에 참여했습니다!
- Why you... - Don't!
- 왜 당신은... - 하지 마세요!
- Hey. - You jerk.
- 여기요. - 멍청아.
What was that, you jerk?
그게 뭐였지, 이 멍청아?
- Kim Chi Yeol! - Hey!
-김치열! - 여기요!
- How dare you? - You started it.
- 어떻게 감히요? - 당신이 시작했어요.
You jerk!
이 바보!
- That's enough! - Have you lost it?
- 충분해요! - 잃어버렸나요?
- What? - That's enough!
- 무엇? - 충분해요!
- Kwon Il Ha. - Hey.
- 권일하. - 여기요.
It was me.
나였어.
Soo Chul...
수철...
and I...
그리고 나는...
have been rigging the polls.
여론조사를 조작해왔습니다.
Kwon Il Ha, what are you saying?
권일하 씨, 무슨 말씀이세요?
Is this true?
이것이 사실입니까?
Soo Chul and I...
수철이랑 나...
were scared at first and wanted to leave.
처음에는 겁이 나서 떠나고 싶었어요.
But the fear only fuelled our anger.
그러나 그 두려움은 우리의 분노를 더욱 키울 뿐이었습니다.
We wanted to wipe out the spheres!
우리는 구체를 없애고 싶었습니다!
You feel the same way, don't you?
당신도 같은 느낌이군요, 그렇죠?
What? You fooled us...
무엇? 당신은 우리를 속였습니다 ...
just to keep hunting the spheres?
단지 구체를 계속 사냥하기 위해서인가요?
What are you barking on about?
당신은 무엇에 대해 짖고 있습니까?
Of course you're angry, but...
물론 화를 내시겠지만...
Kwon Il Ha, are you out of your mind?
권일하, 정신이 나갔나요?
How could you two have done that, though?
그런데 너희 둘이 어떻게 그런 짓을 할 수 있었니?
It would've taken more than you two to rig them.
그것들을 조작하는 데는 너희 둘보다 더 많은 시간이 걸렸을 것이다.
It...
그것은...
It's all my fault.
다 내 잘못이에요.
It was my idea.
그것은 내 생각이었습니다.
You darn prick!
이 빌어먹을 놈아!
Answer me, you prick!
대답해라, 이 새끼야!
Who was it? Who else was in on it?
누구였나요? 또 누가 참여했습니까?
Answer me, darn it!
대답해, 젠장!
Guys.
얘들아.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
Kim Yu Jung?
김유정?
And Cho Jang Soo?
그리고 조장수?
What on earth?
도대체 뭐야?
Why would you do this?
왜 이런 일을 하시겠습니까?
Were you all in on it?
다들 참여하고 계셨나요?
Kim Yu Jung and Cho Jang Soo.
김유정과 조장수.
I don't want to believe it.
나는 그것을 믿고 싶지 않습니다.
Is this why you suggested a poll?
이것이 설문조사를 제안한 이유인가요?
No, they wouldn't have.
아니, 그렇지 않았을 겁니다.
Right?
오른쪽?
Tell us, Yu Jung. Tell us!
말해봐, 유정. 우리에게 말해주세요!
Why can't you say anything?
왜 아무 말도 할 수 없나요?
Tell us why you fooled us this second!
왜 우리를 속였는지 지금 당장 알려주세요!
Tell us!
우리에게 말해주세요!
I couldn't put us all in danger.
나는 우리 모두를 위험에 빠뜨릴 수 없었다.
What are you talking about?
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요?
Is it true that you deceived us?
당신이 우리를 속였다는 것이 사실인가요?
That's insane.
그건 미친 짓이야.
It can't be. I...
그럴 수 없습니다. 나는...
Why, though?
그런데 왜요?
Because...
왜냐면...
Because the CSAT was cancelled.
수능이 취소되었기 때문이죠.
What?
무엇?
Kim Duk Joong, what are you saying?
김덕중, 무슨 소리야?
- What was that? - What?
- 그게 뭐였죠? - 무엇?
- Kim Duk Joong. - What did he just say?
- 김덕중. - 방금 그가 뭐라고 말했어요?
What do you mean by that?
그게 무슨 뜻이에요?
Why was the CSAT cancelled?
수능이 취소된 이유는 무엇인가요?
That's right. The CSAT was cancelled.
좋아요. CSAT가 취소되었습니다.
The other units must've received the radio message.
다른 유닛이 무선 메시지를 수신한 것 같습니다.
Don't you lie to us.
우리에게 거짓말하지 마세요.
That's a lie, isn't it?
그건 거짓말이군요, 그렇죠?
It's true.
사실이에요.
I knew it, darn it!
그럴 줄 알았어, 젠장!
No.
아니요.
The CSAT hasn't been cancelled. Who said that?
CSAT가 취소되지 않았습니다. 누가 그런 말을 했나요?
It's a lie, isn't it?
거짓말이군요, 그렇죠?
There's no way the CSAT would've been cancelled.
수능이 취소될 리가 없습니다.
Young Soo, calm down.
영수야, 진정해.
Tell me that it's a lie!
거짓말이라고 말해주세요!
Kook Young Soo!
국영수!
The CSAT was already cancelled when the spheres first landed.
CSAT는 구체가 처음 착륙했을 때 이미 취소되었습니다.
But how is that important right now?
그런데 그게 지금 어떻게 중요합니까?
It's more important than my life! Darn it!
내 목숨보다 더 중요해요! 젠장!
Don't you know what life until now...
지금까지의 삶이 어떤지 모르시나요...
has been designed around?
주위에 설계되었습니다?
So don't you lie to me.
그러니 나에게 거짓말하지 마세요.
Don't you lie, darn it!
거짓말하지 마세요, 젠장!
Duk Joong, please.
덕중님, 부탁해요.
Please tell me it's not true.
그것이 사실이 아니라고 말해주세요.
Duk Joong.
덕중.
Duk Joong, please.
덕중님, 부탁해요.
Is it true that the CSAT...
수능이 사실인가요...
was cancelled?
취소됐나요?
How did you hear about it when we've lost communication?
우리가 연락이 끊겼을 때 어떻게 그 소식을 들었나요?
(Yongdu Service Area)
(용두 휴게소)
Kids from the science high school came by today.
오늘은 과학고등학교 아이들이 왔습니다.
They received a radio message about the CSAT being cancelled...
수능이 취소된다는 라디오 메시지를 받았는데..
and were on their way to Seoul.
그리고 서울로 가는 중이었습니다.
We said we didn't hear about it...
우리는 그런 얘기를 듣지 못했다고 하더군요...
because our radio died.
우리 라디오가 죽었거든요.
And?
그리고?
They opened it up to fix it for us,
그들은 우리를 위해 그것을 고치기 위해 그것을 열었습니다.
only to find that someone had sabotaged it.
누군가가 그것을 방해했다는 사실을 알게되었습니다.
What are you talking about? Are you serious?
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요? 진심인가요?
Someone deliberately took it off the circuit board.
누군가 고의로 회로 기판에서 떼어냈습니다.
What?
무엇?
Darn it.
젠장.
Why would someone do that?
누군가 왜 그런 짓을 하겠습니까?
Who?
WHO?
Hey. Hey!
여기요. 여기요!
Did you all do this too?
이것도 다들 해보셨나요?
Explain it!
설명해보세요!
You broke the walkie-talkie to hide the cancellation of CSAT?
수능취소를 숨기려고 무전기를 깨뜨렸다고요?
You rigged the vote too!
너도 투표를 조작했구나!
This is absurd.
이것은 터무니없는 일입니다.
Why are there so many issues?
왜 이렇게 문제가 많은 걸까요?
Does anyone have more? Tell me if you have.
더 갖고 있는 사람 있나요? 그런 적이 있으면 말해 보세요.
Say something! Darn it!
뭐라고 말해보세요! 젠장!
We've worked so hard to fix the walkie-talkie.
우리는 무전기를 고치기 위해 열심히 일했습니다.
You saw everything. Why did you do it?
당신은 모든 것을 보았습니다. 왜 그랬어요?
Why?
왜?
Did you want us to die all together?
우리가 다 같이 죽기를 바라셨나요?
Say something! Why?
뭐라고 말해보세요! 왜?
The CSAT isn't cancelled.
CSAT는 취소되지 않습니다.
I doubted it...
의심했는데...
when I heard the news from the walkie-talkie.
무전기에서 소식을 들었을 때.
Even if it was true, I didn't want to believe it.
그것이 사실이더라도 믿고 싶지 않았습니다.
Why did you lie to us?
왜 우리에게 거짓말을 했나요?
Was it important to kill...
죽이는 게 중요한 건지...
more spheres whether we get killed or not?
우리가 죽든 말든 구체가 더 많아지나요?
Are you insane? Are you crazy?
미쳤어? 제정신이에요?
Explain this situation right now.
지금 이 상황을 설명해보세요.
What's all this nonsense?
이 말도 안되는 소리는 다 뭐예요?
The day we heard the news of CSAT cancellation,
수능 취소 소식을 듣던 날,
Soo Chul and I...
수철이랑 나...
were on guard.
경비를 서고 있었습니다.
- What? - I told you.
- 무엇? - 내가 말했잖아.
It has been decided to cancel the CSAT this year.
올해 수능을 취소하기로 결정되었습니다.
The extra points you've earned so far will be applied next year.
지금까지 적립한 추가 포인트는 내년에도 적용됩니다.
So keep the operation going without any deserter. Over.
그러니 탈영병 없이 작전을 계속 진행하세요. 위에.
What? Wait. Hello?
무엇? 기다리다. 안녕하세요?
Hello? Wild Goose. This is Seagull.
안녕하세요? 기러기. 갈매기입니다.
Wild Goose. Respond!
기러기. 대답하다!
Darn it...
젠장...
What nonsense is this?
이게 무슨 말도 안되는 소리입니까?
The CSAT is cancelled, but they want to keep the operation going?
수능이 취소됐는데 계속 운영하고 싶나요?
How many of us got killed until today?
오늘까지 우리 중 몇 명이 죽었을까?
Now the CSAT is cancelled.
이제 수능이 취소되었습니다.
They kept us by using extra points.
그들은 추가 포인트를 사용하여 우리를 유지했습니다.
The jerks are doing whatever they want to.
멍청이들은 자기가 하고 싶은 대로 하고 있어요.
They must think of us as pushovers.
그들은 우리를 만만찮은 사람으로 생각해야 합니다.
Darn it.
젠장.
Darn it!
젠장!
Where are you going?
어디 가세요?
What do you mean? I shall tell others.
무슨 뜻이에요? 나는 다른 사람들에게 말할 것이다.
Wait.
기다리다.
Let's do this instead.
대신 이렇게 해보자.
Is it okay to do this?
이렇게 해도 괜찮나요?
If they find out, they'll want to go home.
만약 그들이 알게 된다면, 집에 가고 싶어할 것입니다.
It doesn't make sense to go to Seoul at this point.
지금 시점에서 서울에 가는 것은 말이 되지 않습니다.
- But... - Tell me.
- 하지만... - 말해보세요.
Kwon Il Ha. Did you stay because of the CSAT?
권일하. 수능 때문에 남았나요?
No, right?
아니, 그렇죠?
You didn't care about extra points.
추가 점수는 신경 쓰지 않았습니다.
Why did you stay?
왜 머물렀나요?
For goodness' sake.
세상에.
This isn't up to adults.
이것은 어른들에게 달려 있는 것이 아닙니다.
It's up to us.
그것은 우리에게 달려 있습니다.
I need to end this war.
이 전쟁을 끝내야 해요.
I'll kill all the spheres.
모든 구체를 죽이겠습니다.
Then I want to go back to school.
그럼 다시 학교로 돌아가고 싶어요.
So we broke the walkie-talkie.
그래서 우리는 무전기를 끊었습니다.
Soo Chul and I were going to keep the secret to ourselves.
그 비밀은 수철이랑 나한테만 비밀로 하기로 했어.
But...
하지만...
(Yongdu Service Area)
(용두 휴게소)
There's only one vote difference.
투표 차이는 단 하나뿐입니다.
At this rate, there will be more votes to go to Seoul.
이대로라면 서울로 가는 표가 더 많아질 것이다.
We promised that since the start.
우리는 처음부터 그렇게 약속했어요.
It's more dangerous to go now. You know that too.
지금 가는 게 더 위험해요. 당신도 그것을 알고 있습니다.
There's no way to communicate.
의사소통할 방법이 없습니다.
What's the point of continuing the duty?
계속해서 임무를 수행하는 이유는 무엇입니까?
No.
아니요.
We need to follow the operational order until we get through.
통과할 때까지 작전 순서를 따라야 합니다.
There'll be more spheres as we get closer to Seoul.
서울에 가까워질수록 더 많은 구체가 생길 것입니다.
It's better to stay here since we're used to being here.
우리는 여기에 익숙해졌기 때문에 여기에 머무르는 것이 더 좋습니다.
There is some food for us to last here too.
여기에도 우리가 먹을 음식이 있습니다.
The others got adjusted too.
다른 사람들도 적응했어요.
If we leave the operational area at our disposal...
작전지역을 우리 마음대로 놔두면...
and don't join them,
그리고 그들과 합류하지 마세요.
we'll be in big trouble.
우리는 큰 문제에 빠지게 될 것입니다.
You're right. But...
당신 말이 맞아요. 하지만...
Let's...
하자...
make a yes vote...
찬성 투표를 하세요...
in advance for the next voting.
다음 투표를 위해 미리
You want to manipulate the vote?
투표를 조작하고 싶나요?
Just until we fix the walkie-talkie.
무전기를 고칠 때까지만요.
We don't know which area is safe. We can't just move without a plan.
우리는 어느 지역이 안전한지 모릅니다. 우리는 계획 없이 그냥 움직일 수 없습니다.
Otherwise, we'll all be in danger.
그렇지 않으면 우리 모두가 위험해질 것입니다.
I don't want to see...
보고 싶지 않아...
anyone dying again.
누구든 또 죽어.
Okay.
좋아요.
Just until we fix the walkie-talkie.
무전기를 고칠 때까지만요.
Just until then.
그때까지만.
What are you doing up at this hour?
이 시간에 뭐하세요?
I agree with the vote rigging.
투표 조작에 동의합니다.
But it will be hard for you two to do it.
하지만 너희 둘이 그렇게 하기는 어려울 것이다.
We'll help.
우리가 도와드리겠습니다.
No. Guys...
아니. 얘들아...
I broke the walkie-talkie.
나는 무전기를 깨뜨렸다.
What? What are you talking about?
무엇? 무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요?
Are you crazy?
제정신이에요?
Wait.
기다리다.
They can only find us through radio.
그들은 라디오를 통해서만 우리를 찾을 수 있습니다.
- They aren't coming. - How do you know that?
- 그 사람들은 안 와요. - 그걸 어떻게 알아요?
The CSAT is cancelled.
CSAT가 취소되었습니다.
- What? - The CSAT is cancelled.
- 무엇? - 수능이 취소되었습니다.
But they want us to continue with the operation.
하지만 그들은 우리가 수술을 계속하길 원해요.
You get what it means, right?
무슨 뜻인지 아시겠죠?
To adults, we're just tools.
어른들에게 우리는 도구일 뿐입니다.
They have no intention to protect us.
그들은 우리를 보호할 의도가 없습니다.
Not at all.
별말씀을요.
I don't care if we're just a tool.
우리가 단지 도구일 뿐이라면 상관없어요.
I'm not going to Seoul.
나는 서울에 가지 않을 것이다.
I'm not sure...
잘 모르겠어요...
if I'll be able to...
내가 할 수 있다면...
face my dead friends.
내 죽은 친구들을 만나세요.
I thought it was nonsense at first.
처음에는 말도 안되는 소리라고 생각했습니다.
But think about it.
하지만 생각해 보세요.
This place is relatively safe.
이 곳은 비교적 안전해요.
It's too dangerous to go to Seoul.
서울에 가기엔 너무 위험해요.
Then is it not dangerous to stay here forever?
그렇다면 여기에 영원히 머무르는 것은 위험하지 않은가?
There are less spheres here.
여기에는 구체가 적습니다.
We have food to endure for a while too.
우리에게도 잠시 버틸 수 있는 음식이 있다.
Stop lying!
거짓말은 그만해!
Hey. What are you trying to do?
여기요. 무엇을 하려고 하시나요?
What's the reason you're keeping us all here?
우리 모두를 여기에 가둬두는 이유가 뭔데요?
You could've told us the truth from the start.
당신은 처음부터 우리에게 진실을 말할 수도 있었습니다.
I thought you'd be upset if you found out...
알면 속상할 줄 알았는데...
that the CSAT was cancelled.
수능이 취소되었다는 소식입니다.
The CSAT?
수능?
Hey. Darn it. What about having the CSAT cancelled?
여기요. 젠장. 수능이 취소되면 어떻게 되나요?
Why would that matter at this point?
이 시점에서 그게 왜 중요할까요?
Do you think CSAT kept us to live like this?
수능이 우리를 이렇게 살게 했다고 생각하시나요?
Why didn't you ask our opinions?
왜 우리 의견을 묻지 않았나요?
Why?
왜?
Who are you to do that?
그런 일을 하는 당신은 누구입니까?
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
Darn it.
젠장.
I can't believe you all now.
나는 지금 당신을 모두 믿을 수 없습니다.
Did you kill Soo Chul because he wanted...
수철이 원해서 죽였나...
to tell the truth?
진실을 말하려고?
- Are you insane? - Yes, we are!
- 미쳤어요? - 네, 그렇습니다!
I'm going crazy because of you all.
너네 때문에 미칠 것 같아
We saw it today.
우리는 오늘 그것을 보았습니다.
Humans are scarier than the spheres.
구체보다 인간이 더 무섭습니다.
You all are...
여러분은...
the same as the criminals.
범죄자와 똑같습니다.
I've really...
난 정말...
thought about it...
그것에 대해 생각했다 ...
hundreds of times.
수백 번.
About the way we can all be together.
우리 모두가 함께 할 수 있는 방법에 대해.
The platoon commander said...
소대장이 말했다..
that we have to protect each other.
서로를 보호해야 한다는 것.
That's how we can survive until the end.
그래야 우리가 끝까지 살아남을 수 있다.
But once you hear that CSAT is cancelled,
그런데 수능이 취소되었다는 소식을 듣고 나면
I thought you would all scatter.
다 흩어질 줄 알았는데
So I wanted to keep you all using the CSAT.
그래서 저는 여러분 모두가 CSAT를 계속 사용하고 싶었습니다.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
I thought we should stick together...
같이 뭉쳐야겠다고 생각했는데...
even by taking severe measures.
가혹한 조치를 취하더라도.
Guys...
여러분...
We...
우리는...
We need to survive.
우리는 살아남아야 합니다.
Right?
오른쪽?
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
I didn't mean to lie to you from the start.
처음부터 당신에게 거짓말을 할 생각은 아니었어요.
You should have...
당신은 ...
told us that in the first place.
우리에게 먼저 그렇게 말했다.
You should've...
넌 그랬어야 했는데...
discussed it with all of us.
우리 모두와 그것에 대해 논의했습니다.
Now, it's too late.
이제는 너무 늦었습니다.
Now,
지금,
what do we do?
우리는 무엇을합니까?
We should go to the shelter, where our parents are.
우리는 부모님이 계신 보호소로 가야 합니다.
How would we know where that is?
그것이 어디에 있는지 어떻게 알 수 있습니까?
We'll have to look for it.
우리는 그것을 찾아야 할 것입니다.
You know...
아시죠...
Do you think Soo Chul actually died in an accident?
수철이 실제로 사고로 사망했다고 생각하시나요?
Or did something happen to him?
아니면 그에게 무슨 일이 일어났나요?
Beats me.
나를 이겼다.
Only Soo Chul will know.
수철만이 알 것이다.
But why?
그런데 왜?
Who?
WHO?
There's no evidence.
증거가 없습니다.
You might regret it...
후회하실 수도 있어요...
once you doubt someone.
일단 누군가를 의심해 보세요.
Why did the adults...
어른들은 왜 그랬을까...
give us rifles?
우리에게 소총을 줄까?
They should have stopped us from holding them.
우리가 그것을 붙잡는 것을 막았어야 했어요.
(Yongdu Service Area)
(용두 휴게소)
Compared to when we first grabbed our rifles,
처음 총을 잡았을 때와 비교해보면,
how much will we have changed...
우리 얼마나 변했을까...
by now?
지금쯤?
All we did was barely survive every day,
우리가 한 일은 매일 간신히 살아남은 것 뿐이었는데,
and we were already turning 20 soon.
그리고 우리는 이제 곧 20살이 되었습니다.
What awaits us at the end of this road?
이 길의 끝에는 무엇이 우리를 기다리고 있을까?
If we safely make it home,
무사히 집에 도착했다면,
can we go back to how we were before we used these rifles?
이 소총을 사용하기 전의 모습으로 돌아갈 수 있을까요?
That day,
그날,
we should not have left the service area.
우리는 서비스 지역을 떠나지 말았어야 했습니다.
(Duty After School)
(방과 후 의무)
Next.
다음.
(Reservist number 1, Kook Young Soo)
(예비 1번 국영수)
Aren't you tired?
피곤하지 않아?
Of course, I am.
물론이죠.
But we're not here to hang out.
하지만 우리는 여기 놀러 온 것이 아닙니다.
Our mission is to eliminate the spheres.
우리의 임무는 구체를 제거하는 것입니다.
We can go back once we finish the mission.
임무를 마치면 돌아갈 수 있습니다.
That's true, but everyone is exhausted...
그렇긴한데 다들 지쳐가는데...
after the platoon commander died.
소대장이 죽은 후.
We just need to remember our training.
우리는 훈련을 기억하면 됩니다.
Let's be honest.
솔직하게 말해보자.
I bet all seniors in this country have similar extra points.
이 나라의 모든 선배들은 비슷한 가산점을 갖고 있을 거라 장담합니다.
Then, what would be the point?
그렇다면 요점은 무엇입니까?
I have to finish the mission to stay on top.
정상에 오르려면 임무를 완수해야 해요.
Don't underestimate those extra points.
추가 점수를 과소평가하지 마세요.
It will make a difference in the end.
결국에는 변화가 생길 것입니다.
You'll take the CSAT to go to college after this, won't you?
너 이 다음에 대학에 가려면 수능을 쳐 볼 거야, 그렇지?
Well, I guess so.
글쎄요. 그런 것 같아요.
But...
하지만...
Young Soo, why are you so obsessed with college?
영수 씨, 왜 그렇게 대학에 집착해요?
Well, people normally say,
글쎄요, 사람들은 보통 이렇게 말합니다.
"I'd like..."
"나는 좋겠다..."
"my family to stay the same."
"내 가족은 그대로 유지됩니다."
But I want the opposite.
하지만 나는 그 반대를 원한다.
What do you mean by that?
그게 무슨 뜻이에요?
My mom and dad work from dawn till dusk.
우리 엄마 아빠는 새벽부터 황혼까지 일해요.
When they come home, we don't have the luxury of talking.
그들이 집에 오면 우리는 이야기를 나눌 여유가 없습니다.
They just go straight to bed.
그들은 그냥 곧장 잠자리에 듭니다.
And at dawn,
그리고 새벽에,
while my parents groan in pain,
부모님이 고통스러워 신음하시는 동안,
I study with earplugs on.
귀마개를 끼고 공부해요.
Sure, war is dreadful.
물론, 전쟁은 무서운 것입니다.
But do you know what's more dreadful?
그런데 더 무서운 게 뭔지 아시나요?
It's poverty.
빈곤입니다.
You guys don't know...
너희들은 모르지...
what it's like to be really poor.
정말 가난하다는 게 어떤 건지.
My family...
우리 가족...
can never work our way out of this destitution...
결코 이 빈곤에서 벗어날 수 없습니다...
unless we win the lottery ticket.
우리가 복권에 당첨되지 않는 한.
For my younger siblings to go to college as well...
동생들도 대학에 갈 수 있도록...
and talk about what happened that day at the table...
그리고 테이블에서 그날 있었던 일을 이야기해 보세요.
To have that normal life...
그런 평범한 삶을 살려면...
that's insignificant to others,
남들에겐 별것 아닌 일이지만
I must get accepted by a good college...
좋은 대학에 합격해야 하는데...
and get a job at a good company.
그리고 좋은 회사에 취직하세요.
Can you delete this video?
이 영상을 삭제해주실 수 있나요?
I shouldn't have said those.
그런 말은 하지 말았어야 했는데.
I'll do the interview next time.
인터뷰는 다음에 할게요.
(Duty After School)
(방과 후 의무)